<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An ordinance for uniting Scotland into one common-wealth with England. Wednesday April 12. 1654. Ordered by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Henry Scobell, Clerk of the Council.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1063_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209584</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868452</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868452</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169196</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74516)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169196)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 158:E1063[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An ordinance for uniting Scotland into one common-wealth with England. Wednesday April 12. 1654. Ordered by his Highness the Lord Protector, and his Council, that this ordinance be forthwith printed and published. Henry Scobell, Clerk of the Council.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Lord Protector (1653-1658 : O. Cromwell)</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Council of State.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 253-260, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William du-Gard and Henry Hills, Printers to His Highness the Lord Protector,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169196:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ORDINANCE FOR UNITING SCOTLAND INTO ONE COMMON-WEALTH WITH ENGLAND.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>Wedneſday April</hi> 12. 1654.</p>
            <p>ORdered by his Highneſs the Lord Protector, and his Council, That this Ordinance be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Henry Scobell,</hi> Clerk of the Council.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>William du-Gard</hi> and <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printers to His Highneſs the Lord Protector, 1654.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="ordinance">
            <pb facs="tcp:169196:2"/>
            <pb n="253" facs="tcp:169196:2"/>
            <head>AN ORDINANCE FOR UNITING SCOTLAND Into one Commonwealth with ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Is Highneſs the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, &amp;c.</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how much it might conduce to the glory of God, and the Peace and welfare of the People in this whole Iſland, That af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:169196:3"/>all thoſe late unhappy Warres and Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, the People of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the People of <hi>England,</hi> into one Commonwealth, and under one Government; And finding that in <hi>December</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred fifty and one, the Parlament then ſitting did ſend Commisſioners into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to invite the People of that Nation unto ſuch a happy Vnion, who proceeded ſo far therein, that the Shires and Burroughs of <hi>Scotland,</hi> by their Deputies convened at <hi>Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keith,</hi> and again at <hi>Edenburgh,</hi> did accept of the ſaid Vnion, and aſſent thereunto. For the compleating and perfecting of which Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Be it Ordained, And it is Ordained by his Highneſs the Lord Protector of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereto belonging, by and with the advice and conſent of his Council, That all the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of the Iſles of <hi>Orkney</hi> and <hi>Zethland,</hi> and of all the Dominions and Territories belonging unto <hi>Scotland,</hi> are and ſhall be, and are hereby In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corporated into, Conſtituted, Eſtabliſhed, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and Confirmed one Commonwealth with <hi>England;</hi> And in every Parlament to be held Succesſively for the ſaid Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, thirty perſons ſhall be called from, and ſerve for <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the more effectual preſervation of this Vnion, and the freedom, and ſafety of the People of this Common-wealth ſo uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Be it Ordained, And it is Ordained by the Authority aforeſaid, That all the people of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and of the Iſles of <hi>Orkney</hi>
               <pb n="255" facs="tcp:169196:3"/>and <hi>Zethland,</hi> and of all the Dominions and Territories belonging unto <hi>Scotland,</hi> of what Degree or Condition ſoever, be diſcharged of all Fealty, Homage, Service and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which is or ſhall be pretended Due unto any of the Iſſue and Poſterity of <hi>Charles Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>art,</hi> late King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Claiming under him; And that <hi>Charles Stuart,</hi> Eldeſt Son, and <hi>James,</hi> called Duke of <hi>York,</hi> ſecond Son, and all other the Iſſue and Poſterity of the ſaid late King, and all and every perſon and perſons, pretending Title, from, by, or under him, are and be diſabled to hold or enjoy the Crown of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and other the Dominions thereunto belonging, or any of them, or to have the Name, Title, Stile, or Dignity of King, or Queen of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to have and enjoy the Power and Dominion of the ſaid Kingdom and Dominions, or any of them, or the Honors, Mannors, Lands, Tenements, Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Hereditaments belonging or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the ſaid Crown of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or other the Dominions aforeſaid, or to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, any Law, Statute, Vſage, Ordinance or Cuſtome in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the contrary hereof in any wiſe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>And it is further Ordained by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie aforeſaid, That the ſaid Office, Stile, Dignity, Power and Authority of King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and all right of the Three Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to convocate or Aſſemble in any General Convocation or Parlament, and all
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:169196:4"/>Conventional and Parlamentary Authority in <hi>Scotland,</hi> as formerly eſtabliſhed, and all Lawes, Vſages, and Cuſtomes, Ordaining, Conſtituting, or Confirming the ſame, ſhall be, and are hereby, and from henceforth aboliſhed and utterly taken away, and made null and void.</p>
            <p>And that this Vnion may take its more full effect and Intent, Be it further Ordained by the Authority aforeſaid, That the Arms of <hi>Scotland, viz.</hi> a Croſs, commonly called Saint <hi>Andrews</hi> Croſs, be received into and born from henceforth in the Arms of this Commonwealth, as a Badge of this Vnion; and that all the Publique Seals, Seals of Office, and Seals of Bodies, Civil or Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, in <hi>Scotland,</hi> which heretofore carried the Arms of the Kings of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſhall from henceforth inſtead thereof, carry the Arms of this Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained by the authority aforeſaid, That all Cuſtomes, Exciſe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Impoſts for Goods tranſported from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> by Sea or Land, are and ſhall be ſo far taken off, and diſcharged, as that all Goods for the future ſhall paſs as free, and with like Privileges, and with the like Charges and Burdens, from <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England,</hi> as goods paſſing from port to port, or place to place in <hi>England;</hi> and that all Goods ſhall and may paſs between <hi>Scotland,</hi> and any other part of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,
<pb n="257" facs="tcp:169196:4"/>or the Dominions thereof, with the like Privileges, Freedome, Charges and Burdens, as ſuch Goods do, or ſhall paſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>England,</hi> and the ſaid parts and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, any Law, Statute, Vſage or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to the contrary thereof in any wiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. And that all goods prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by any Law now in force in <hi>England</hi> to be tranſported out of <hi>England</hi> to any Forein parts, or imported, ſhall be, and hereby are prohibited to be tranſported or imported, by the ſame Law, and upon the ſame penalties, out of <hi>Scotland</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Forein parts aforeſaid, or from any Forein parts into <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That all Ceſſes, publique Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions and Taxations whatſoever, be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, taxed, and levyed from henceforth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionably from the whole people of this Commonwealth ſo united.</p>
            <p>And further, to the end that all Dominion of Tenures and Superiorities importing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude and Vaſſallage may likewiſe be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> Be it further Declared and Ordained by the Authority aforeſaid, That all Heritors, Proprietors, and Poſſeſſors of Lands in <hi>Scotland,</hi> or the Dominions there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging, and their Heirs, ſhall from and after the twelfth day of <hi>April</hi> in the year of our Lord one thouſand ſix hundred fifty and four hold their reſpective Lands of the reſpective Lord and Lords by Deed, Charter, Patent or Enfeoffment, to be
<pb n="258" facs="tcp:169196:5"/>renewed upon the death of every Heritor, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietor, Poſſeſſor (as now they do) to his Heir or Heirs, by and under ſuch yearly Rents, Boons, &amp; Annual ſervices, as are mentioned or due by any Deeds, Patents, Charters or Enfeofments now in being, of the reſpective Lands therein expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or by vertue thereof enjoyed without ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring, doing or performing any other Duty, Service, Vaſſallage or Demand whatſoever by reaſon or occaſion of the ſaid Lands, or any the Clauſes, or Covenants in the ſaid Deeds, Charters, Patents or Enfeoffments contained, ſaving what is hereafter, herein and hereby particularly expreſſed and declared, That is to ſay, Heriots where the ſame are due, Fines (certain where the ſame is already certain, and where the Fine is uncertain, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Fines) upon the death of the Lord, and upon the death or alienation of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, or any of them, where the ſame have uſually been paid, which ſaid Fine (not being already certain) ſhall not at any time exceed one years value of the Lands, and alſo doing ſute and ſervice to ſuch Court &amp; Courts Baron, as ſhall be conſtituted in <hi>Scotland,</hi> in ſuch man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as is Ordained by one other Ordinance, Entituled, <hi>An Ordinance for Erecting Courts Baron in <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>And be it Ordained by the Authority afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, That all and every the Heritors, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors, and Poſſeſſors aforeſaid, and their Heirs, are and ſhall be from henceforth for ever diſcharged of all Fealty, Homage, Vaſſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage and Servitude, which is, or ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:169196:5"/>due from them, or any of them, unto any their Lords or Superiors whatſoever, claiming Dominion or Iuriſdiction over them, by vertue of the ſaid Patents, Charters, Deeds or Enfeoffments, and other rights thereof, or of any Clauſes or Conditions therein contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, other than as is before Declared and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained. And that all the ſaid Superiorities, Lordſhips and Iuriſdictions (other than as aforeſaid) ſhall be, and are hereby aboliſhed, taken off, and diſcharged; and that all and every the ſaid Deeds, Patents, Charters, and Enfeofments in that behalf, be, and are hereby declared, and made ſo far void and null; And particularly, That all and every the Heritors, and others the perſons aforeſaid, and their Heirs, are and ſhall be for ever here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after freed and diſcharged of, and from all ſutes, and appearing at or in any their Lords or Superiors Courts of Iuſtitiary, Rega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Stuartry, Barony, Bayliary, Herita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Sherifſhip, Heritable Admiralty, all which, together with all other Offices heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, or for life, are hereby aboliſhed, and taken away; and that all and every the Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and perſons aforeſaid, and their Heirs, are and ſhall be for ever hereafter freed and diſcharged, of, and from all Military ſervice, and perſonal attendance upon any their Lords or Superiors in Expeditions or Travels, and of all Caſualties, of Wards Lands formerly held of the King or other Superiors, and of the Marriage, ſingle and double avail thereof, Non-Entries, Compoſitions for entries, and of all Rights and Caſualties payable, if they
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:169196:6"/>be demanded, onely or upon the committing of any Clauſes irritant. And that the ſaid Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and perſons aforeſaid be now and from henceforth conſtrued, reputed, adjudged, and declared free and acquitted thereof, and of and from all and all manner of holding ſutes, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſervices perſonal or real, and demands whatſoever, (other than is before declared and Ordained) notwithſtanding the preſent Tenor of any their Deeds, Patents, Enfeofments; or any Clauſes, Articles or Covenants therein contained or mentioned to the contrary in any wiſe; And that in time to come all and every Clauſe, Covenant, Article, Condition or thing to the contrary hereof, ſhall be omitted out of all ſuch Deeds, Patents, Charters and Enfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offments.</p>
            <p>And be it further Ordained, That all For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures, Eſcheats, ſimple, or of life, Rent Baſtardy, and laſt Heir, which heretofore eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheated, forfeited and fell to the King, Lords of Regalitie, or other Superiors, ſhall from henceforth fall, eſcheat, and forfeit to the Lord Protector of the Commonwealth for the time being.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Wedneſday April 12. 1654.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>ORdered by his Highneſs the Lord Protector, and His Council, That this Ordinance be forthwith Printed and Publiſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Henry Scobell,</hi> Clerk of the Council.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
